okay
hello and welcome everyone it is january
2022.
we're here in academ lab model stream
number 5.1
with pietro mazzaglia and tim verbellen
so this is going to be a model stream
presentation and discussion on their
recent work contrastive active inference
we're going to have a presentation
section and then a discussion
so please feel free to ask any questions
during the presentation that we can
address in the discussion and tim and
pietro thanks a ton we really appreciate
you joining to share your work so please
take it away and thanks again
yeah thanks daniel for uh for inviting
us as well so uh i'm timothy and
together with the
colleague pietro we'll talk on our work
on contrastive active inference
so maybe first to um
set the scene why are we
looking at active inference
uh well basically our lab wants to build
intelligent agents and so from that
perspective we noticed early on if you
want to build something intelligent
it needs to be embodied it needs to be
interacting with its environments
and then it's a small step of course you
know interactive inference where
basically your your agent needs to
understand the environment it's
interacting with and and need to build
the model basically
so
i'll first give an overview on on active
inference and the way that that we
approach this
um a lot a lot of this material has also
been covered uh in a previous model
stream i think number number three uh so
if you want more details you can pick up
that one again
um and so then afterwards um uh pieter
will take over and he will um go into
the
details of the contrastive approach to
active inference so let's get started
so basically
active inference it's a process theory
of the brain
and basically it says that your brain
are the agents
he builds
or he builds generative model of the
environment which is basically a joint
probably distribution over observations
so think that you can see or experience
actions which we didn't know the scale
and then um states or um
yeah
hidden states of the environment
so basically you have your agent that is
separate from the environment
and it can do actions it can interact
with the environment
and this gives rise to new uh
observations and so the idea of the
generative model is biscuit agent
figures out
which are kind of the the hidden states
that
the change by my actions and that gave
rise to my uh observations and if you
can build such a model then basically uh
this enables the agents to plan uh some
actions
to to bring the agent to some preferred
observations or outcomes and support but
so the
crucial bits is basically how do you get
this model um
of what happens
if i do my actions how does this
influence the state and and how does
this influence the outcomes that i see
and so the crucial part connective
inference is twofold so first of all it
says okay
this is what the agent does and it does
so by optimizing so-called free energy
which is an upper bound and surprise or
prediction error so basically
[Music]
the generative model allows the agent to
predict the outcomes that it will see
that it will witness
and um the better these match your
actual observations the more happier you
are
as an agent
and crucially you will also select the
actions that will minimize
the free energy you expect in the future
and so we'll
dig a bit into the mods
um
just to to set the scene uh on the one
hand notation-wise so that we all know
what folds and s's and a's are but also
to then
see the move that piet will make from
the let's say valera active inference
presentation towards a more contrastive
formulation of of
the active influence object reality
objective
so we start off with uh setting the c
with a generative model so uh it's it's
a bit laid out uh the the diagram of the
agents and the environment that was on
previous slides so basically this
unfolds over time so you are in a
certain state that gives rise to a
certain observation and then given an
action on your previous state you
basically move ahead
to
the next state
and this process unfolds over time
and you can see um some of the um
the circles are covered gray and these
are basically the things that you can
observe
so you know the actions that you did up
until now
and you know the observations that you
saw up until now
and all the rest is basically for you to
infer so you can only refer the hidden
states until now
but you can also try to infer the hidden
states of the future the actions that
you want to take or the observations
that you will experience
and so basically the um
the so-called joint model or joint
distribution over the sequence of
observation states and action is then
basically factorized as follows so you
have a prior over actions
uh you have a lightweight model so
uh
so yeah so you have prior over action so
this basically determines yeah what is
the probability you take certain actions
certain time
you have
some transition probabilities so what is
the probability that i
i will transition to this next state
given my previous state and the action i
did and you have the likelihood model
which basically says
yeah given the state i am um
which observation i will see and so this
basically covers the so-called markov
assumption that your observation that
you see uh at this time step it only
depends on your hidden state and it does
not really directly depend on anything
else
uh because if you know your your your
current in state then you know the
observation you will see
so that's basically what's but it's
reflected here
but of course as an agent
having this generative model this allows
you to to
assess how likely is a sequence of
observations for example and it allows
you to predict
given these actions what will happen but
one crucial bit of course is still the
inverse of this model like
given that i saw these observations that
i did these actions
which is my current state um and and
this is
basically uh non-trivial
so even if you have the exact strength
model inverting this is typically
intractable
and so that's why why in active
inference you uh you resort to variation
inference and you just say okay
i just assume that i can build a model
the so-called bricks and posterior model
and this is the thing that will uh tell
me given certain observations
what is my probability to be in a
certain state
so this is what's depicted here so yeah
we introduce this q
and q is basically a variational
approximate here so can be any
distribution you can choose it
and you just say okay
um
given some observation i want to have
the best estimate for
the state i am in
and
the free energy principle genesis states
if that's what you want then this is
easy you just uh optimize the free
energy which is the note f here and it's
basically expectation over uh states uh
generated by your
personal posterior the expectation over
the the difference between the local
accuracy of your approximate posterior
and look like of the gif model
and if you can minimize that that
basically means that you will have
um
the best explanation for the
observations you see but at the same
time you also have the best
examples here for the true one and we're
not going to go to the whole derivation
of
this flow but basically
uh you can convert this to the the
second equation line and this is the one
that we we use most often
in our models which is basically clear
versions between
this
approximate posterior so basically what
is the state i am given the observations
i saw
and um
uh
this briar that basically says
this is my my guess
that i am in the states given my
previous state and action so i don't
know the observation yet
but i want to have uh the best guess uh
without my observation and if i see the
observation i don't want my beliefs to
completely switch because then probably
there's something wrong with my model
and then you have the second term which
is the uh
the like return this is basically the
accuracy of your model or how good are
you at reconstructing the outcomes
so
um
this is all for the past uh basically or
up until your current time step so you
know the observations you saw and you
can evaluate the free energy and then
you can basically update your model
in order to
uh
to minimize this thing but of course you
also need to know your actions you want
to look into the future
and so
if you look into the future then we talk
about the expected free energy
and so here uh we didn't we we used by
the shorthand for the sequence of
actions into the future i also switched
from d to daw just to denotes that we
are talking about future time steps
basically but other than that same but
the
important bit is now that in the
expectation
now you don't have expectations only
over states but also over outcomes
because you you couldn't sense
uh
your observations yet so you don't know
them so you can just kind of
do an expectation over anything that
could happen
and
and then uh the move that
is made in active inference
is basically that uh
you on the one hand form uh the term
which they call or which we call the
instrumental value
or realizing preferences
and it's basically stating that okay as
an agent for future outcomes
i have some prior that i think that i
will
regardless what happens that i think i
will realize it's kind of your your
preferred outcomes let's say you can
also cause this more like homeostasis so
i want my body temperature to be uh
37 degrees celsius so my expectation
before knowing anything is that it will
be
37 degrees and hence i will act in order
to make it so so that's a bit reflected
here like you you disregard
the um the dependency on your future
actions you just say okay my prior is
that's this is what i expect
uh so this becomes the instrumental
value
and then the second assumption is
basically that
your approximate posterior model
is basically very very close to the true
posterior so that you have a good
approximation then you can
rewrite
it's in the second term
which basically
means that you have on the one hand and
the third that says
this is my belief or the state given
the actions
i will do
and the other thing is
also a belief about future states given
the actions and some certain outcomes
that i expect to see so basically it
says
what would be the information that i get
from
looking for certain
outcomes and it's kind of an epistemic
value or an information game
which can drive you to to explore
basically you want to have
if
if you don't know how to get to your
preferred state at least you want to get
to state to
states that give you more information on
on where you are
go first
often says it's like the owl that needs
foods so what do you do do you eat first
or do you search for prey first and so
the epistemic value is basically
searching for prey it's like where
should i go to
to to get more information on where the
play is and then once you know where it
is then you can realize your preferences
and uh
go towards the towers of free basically
so
how how does the action selection works
then well basically you want to select
the actions that minimize your expected
free energy so at each time step
first thing you do is you use your
approximate model to uh to estimate your
burn state it's like knowing
in which state am i now given my latest
observation
then you can evaluate the expected free
energy for uh
for each
pulse your plan so for
any future sequence of actions you can
evaluate
and the expected free energy
and then this basically results in a
belief over policy so you basically
take the the mind the negative expected
free energy you multiply with this
precision parameter which just states
how yeah
how how much confidence you have that
your expected free energy is correct
basically and then you use this the soft
mix function so basically just
it just says
um
the
the policies that have low expected free
energy are the ones that are most likely
basically that's that's the only thing
this formula says and then you refer the
next action according to this you just
select the next action for the sequence
that you think
will give you the
the minimum the minimum expected 3mg and
that's how it goes and then you you take
this action you get a new observation
and a process
[Music]
so one crucial point in in our work is
that
uh it all starts with this genetic model
and it's approximate model and um
typically um
you can and you have a certain problem
and you know how the problem
uh looks like what what the observations
are what the hidden state might be and
then you can you can really pinpoint and
write down the exact model and start
optimizing but in our case this is often
not true if you if you look at the robot
that drives around and gets camera
inputs for example yeah what is the
state space that you need to um
that you need to track how do you
convert these pixels to the state space
so all these things are yeah
they're just not there yet and the goal
in our work is that yeah can we
can we completely start from scratch and
learn this
and for this we use
deep neural networks to act as function
approximators to actually um
provide us with these these models and
we optimize the parameters of these
neural nets
also by minimizing the free energy
that's that's the core id that's it
so how does it look like we call this
an artificial word model so we start off
with uh observations and actions so
these can be
pixels basically so uh an
n by m matrix of numbers let's say
and actions which could be any action
factor it could be your velocity or
whatever your agent can do
and these numbers are put into a neural
net which we call the encoder and this
basically reflects this approximate
posterior this is just saying given my
previous state
action and my current observation it
outputs
a probabilistic state representation
which is basically the means and the
variances of multivariate versions
and then
we have a second neural net which we
call the transition model and this is
then
[Music]
saying yeah what what will happen if i
do a certain action how will my state
evolve if i if i do a certain action
now finally we also have the the decoder
or the likelihood model that then
outputs given states some observation so
in case of an image for example this
will generate you a new image
and the goal is of course to
have the best predictions
possible so if you look at the free
energy
formula again in this case
it's again you have this likelihood
which basically just says
and
given the the output of the decoders or
the generic image i just want to have
this close to the actual image that you
then uh see basically so it's just a
reconstruction loss in terms of a neural
net let's say
and the second term
sorry
second term is a gal divergence between
the distribution that you generate from
the encoder
and the distribution that you generate
from the transition model basically
so we apply this on a number of cases
which also um
were seen in the previous model stream
so just to give you some intuition so
first thing was uh the mounting core
problems just which is a basic control
problem so here
the sensory input is the position you
are with the card
you basically have to infer
not only the position you're in but also
the momentum you have the velocity you
have and so you can see that
uh
on the right you can see the model
predicting all likely trajectories
for going left or right and you can see
how in the beginning it's not sure on
the velocity so it's it's very spread
out in
in what it will predict but the more
information it gets the more it kind of
collapses to yeah i'm pretty sure that
this is the behavior that will happen
and then you can use this to
to drive the agents towards
a preferred state in this case the
the flag
the second one
was using the
car racer environment so here you get
these
uh
observations are now just pixels from
from this uh
game
and the preferred state of the car was
to be in the center of the track
and so you can see how it actually
infers the actions that will bring it to
uh to the center of the track uh
and it might even cut corners in order
to reach the preferred state a bit
faster and finally we also did this on
on the robots navigating our lab
where we equipped it with
a number of sensor modalities so you can
see a camera but also
a front facing lighter and also a radar
range doppler so the radar range doppler
basically gives you
in the y-axis
the range
and in the
x-axis the the velocity of the
reflections basically
and here you can see how in the
beginning
we feed it with a number of observations
and then we basically let the model
imagine what could happen so these are
real observations and now
it basically imagines what it will see
if it turns around for example because
it actually learns like basic uh
dynamics basic behavior
um of of all these sensor models so it's
pretty cool
okay so what are the limitations of this
thing
well there are two core limitations that
we address uh in the work of pietro so
the first one is
we
we use this this recon pixel wax
reconstruction
board to uh to learn the model but also
to define your preferred state like this
is the image that you want to see and
try to make it happen
but the problem is that means where
error in pixel
in terms of pixels is not really the
best metric so for example if you have
the
the left image
and you want to assess how good
an image is similar to
that one
we have two examples here on the right
and you can see that the the same image
with some salt and pepper noise is
actually scoring worse in terms of mean
squared error than an image where the
the two two
joint arm is actually uh
incorrect so
although
in terms of behavior the the left one is
better in terms of means great error the
the right one is better so that's of
course problematic if you want to
control the arm towards the goal
and then the second limitation is that
if you need to evaluate the expected
free energy for a huge number of
potential trajectories potential actions
you can do then of course this becomes
intractable as the number increases
and so the the ways that we coped with
this in in the contrastive work is on
the one hand
instead of using a pixel-wise
reconstruction error is to use
contrastive learning instead
how exactly this works
in the in the next few slides
and then the second thing is instead of
evaluating the expected free energy
for all the policies
we basically amortize the policy
selection scheme so we also train neural
net to output actions given during the
stage
and so with that
uh we can now shift
to ghetto who will talk about the
contrastive formulation of the
principle
thank you tim
alright so thank you daniel for having
us and uh thank you team i hope you can
hear me well
okay so
i'll try to share my screen now
okay
all right so
now i will talk about our
recent work contrastive active inference
so
this work was recently published that
now rips 2021 so
very recently it came out like
last month and let's
start delving into it
so the
the setting that we discuss in inactive
inference is very similar to the
reinforcement learning one
with the difference that in
reinforcement learning
uh the
all behavior learning is driven by
rewards so the agent receive a reward
function
and
positive rewards should reinforce
positive behaviors while negative
rewards should penalize
the agent to avoid to the states and
actions
however one of the problems comes with
reinforcement learning is that
in order to actually learn from rewards
you need a rework function and that's
not always easy to have for instance a
steam mentioned
especially when the state is not known
in advance so the agent doesn't exactly
know it states it's difficult
in that case to design a reward function
because you're not sure of what the
agent knows and how it can assess its
performance compared to the environment
so
we instead focus on active inference in
inactive inference the agent separates
to the
the principle of minimizing free energy
as we we have just
seen so
the the principle of minimizing free
energy actually enables two things the
one thing is to learn
uh a model of the word we we call this
an artificial world model in our work a
steam show
and the other objective is to minimize
the free energy in the future by trying
to achieve
uh
some preferred outcomes of the agent so
we assume that the agent does some
preferred outcome distribution that he
wants to achieve and
this goal will be in the future to
actually achieve these preferred
outcomes
so the
the environment setting we discuss is
that's one of our pndp so a partially
observable marketplacing process
so just to recap we have observation
that
the agent receives he has to infer the
internal state of the environment which
is not
and then there's action which are
actually known for the past but the
agent should infer or
somehow choose among
a set of possible actions in the future
so this is just a summary of what the
the an artificial word model looks like
so as as we've seen in the previous
slides we have an encoder that encodes
the information from an observation we
focus on visual environments so
here we have uh again an image which is
basically n-by-n metrics so the encoder
could be for instance a convolutional
neural network
in our case then we have uh the the
hidden state model which which takes the
previous state and the previous action
and in particular in our case here we
use some some form of recurrent neural
network model in order to keep observing
the history of the environment and then
we have the decoder that
computes reconstruction of the the
observation of the current state so it
tries to encode uh inside the hidden
states of as much information as
possible
from what it comes from the from the
observation
so the problem with uh reconstruction is
that computing them especially in visual
environments is is quite complicated
because you need
big models that have a very good
representational capacity and also the
models cannot be a hundred percent
accurate as in uh lowest low dimensional
settings because
for instance predicting
an image pixel by pixel is practically
very invisible so it very rarely happens
so let's go on example here so a few a
few weeks ago i was uh i was training uh
bae like model so like uh
a model similar to this one on the left
so where we have the this
encoder decoder architecture on uh on an
atari game the
breakout game
and try to to learn an eden state to
to learn action on top of the the
interstate the problem is that
the the reconstruction of the the vae so
we're actually pretty bad in that they
were losing very important information
about the game so for instance
it was
kind of able so with some uncertainty to
model where the puddle of the game is
but it wasn't able uh to model where the
ball is which is actually
one of the two most important details in
order to actually be able
to play so even adding the reward
function in this case so having the the
the game score available uh the agent
wasn't able to learn the task because of
uh of the state which was lacking the
most important information in order to
to keep improving
so this is one issue that we try to
overcome in our work
and the second part of active inference
involves learning to pursue the
preferred outcome
so in order to pursue preferred outcomes
active inference agent
will do two things one try to minimize
uh
the distance with respect to these
preferred outcomes but on the other way
also minimize the ambiguity respect to
the environment
so normally this is done by trying to
match uh these the two distributions or
trying to to match as we saw with
uh with a kill divergence try to match
the distribution of the imagined outcome
with the preferred outcomes distribution
however again in a high-dimensional
setting this can be quite complex
because uh how do you define a
distribution on a 9-dimensional image
could it be for instance just a center
gaussian around the
pixel so with the
with the mean being the pixel value and
then some fixed standard deviation but
in that case we we get into troubles
because we have the same issue discussed
before with for instance having this
kind of call here and a noisy
observation like this which actually
adds an eye and higher mean square error
compared to to an image that is very
distant from the goal
and this kind of situation especially
when using reconstruction or in more
realistic settings are very very likely
because for instance you can you can
think that the center
image
is actually just a reconstruction of the
model which is not 100 accurate so that
could be the case and indeed the agent
will be confused and he will think that
it's not achieving the goal compared to
maybe for instance a past observation
but if it seemed it was actually
actually closer to the goal or again
when there is some some noise in the
environment in real world setup like
also robotic we always add this noise
into the observation so it's hard to
uh to match a preferred outcome in a
internet dimensional setting so we we
also try to
to overcome this issue here
so what we do propose is to use
contrastive learning
uh contrastive learning is a
is a mechanism popular in the
unsupervised learning scene that we will
discuss more in depth in a few moments
so the the
the objective that we want to to have
with our method are to avoid
reconstruction in
learning the word model so we don't have
any more the decoder here as we see on
the right
then we want to be able to match
preferred outcomes in a lower
dimensionality space because we have
seen that uh net dimensionality that's
problematic and also we
we would like the this low dimensional
state to be somehow representative of
the task so that we when we match
our goal in this low dimensional state
we are actually doing something that
actually brings us closer to the actual
preferred outcome that we we want to
achieve in the i dimensional setting
so
let's
let's try to compare
to see what are the difference in
between using the likelihood active
inference model and the contrastive
model so
the idea in the likelihood active
inference model is that we want to
maximize the accuracy of reconstruction
so basically this this means that we
have this decoder that maximizes this
uh
maximum likelihood of the the
observation given the state so we want
the state to
to
to maximize the information that it
contains about the observation basically
in contrasting learning we
in contrasting active inference we do
something different so instead of trying
to reconstruct
the current observation
we try to
compress with the encoder again this
observation
and compare it to all the other uh to
not all the other as we'll see in a
while because it's invisible but many
many
other samples that represent something
different so that we in the in the
latent space in this compressed space
we want
our
state and the compressed image to be
very close
uh while uh this our state should be
very distant from all the other images
so
we
we are indeed maximizing the similarity
with this
with the corresponding sample this is
here called the positive sample where we
want to minimize the similarities to
maximize the distance against all the
other samples that are called negative
samples
in contrastive learning so as we'll see
also in
in a moment this this mechanism here
maximizes the lower bound of the mutual
information so we are basically trying
to maximize the information in between
corresponding
observation and state
while
minimizing the information with respect
to to all the other negative pairs
so as we've seen uh
before the the free energetic past can
be summarized
with this equation here so here i'm just
uh
talking about one time a one moment in
discrete time steps so instead the
team presented for all sequences by
using the tilde notation well here we're
just considering one time steps
at a time so
as we
as we have seen the free energy is
basically uh
an upper bond on the surprisal
information that we we want to to
minimize so we minimize free energy in
order to
minimize the surprise of the agent and
the ear is is actually evident that
we have this evidence spawn so the the
scale divergence is always greater or
equal to zero we wanted to
basically to
to reach zero hypothetically in order to
minimize this uh
this evidence bound
and uh this can also be rewritten uh in
a way it is more practical to implement
it so by having
the the likelihood of the observation
given the state which actually means the
accuracy of our model and having again
the complexity of the model which is
the the kl divergence between
our variational distribution q
uh which we
we we use q of f given o which is
basically using the auto encoding uh
variation of a variational uh posterior
so this is uh
as typical as is done in uh in
variational encoders so when you
when you try to infer the parameters of
your posterior distribution by using the
corresponding observation
and then we we want to minimize the
child divergence between this uh auto
encoded posterior and the our prior
about the
the current or future state we can say
given the the past state and actions
and in our case in particular we
generally
learn this this prior so we don't just
use a
a uniform prior state but we will learn
uh our priors to be predictive
of what the state is given uh the past
states so it can basically seem like
for machine learning prediction as a as
a conditional uh variation of the
encoder
with with contrastive learning what we
try to do is as i said to maximize state
similarity uh with
the correct and corresponding
observations of our positive sample
while minimizing with the other
this
means again that we want to
maximize the mutual information between
the positive sample
and the corresponding state and
minimizing the information with the
negative samples
this can be written like this so
the
noise contrastive
estimation so nch that's the
abbreviation
basically provides uh
again a lower bound on the mutual uh
information uh so where we where we see
that we basically have like like a soft
max so
over the over all the the
the observation state what does it mean
so uh for each a pair of state and
observation
we want uh this value so the value of
this critic this this critic function f
to be as
high as possible or we want it to be a
very low
respect to the other so that actually
the exponential of this
compared to the sum of all the other
exponential is higher with the
corresponding exhibition and
very low with the rest
so this is basically saying that uh that
you'd want matching pairs to be to be
very close and distant pairs to
to a very very low value
and the the
this
this lower bound
is is an approximation normally when we
take
a number of samples key from
a joint distribution that we define
uh between x and y in particular in our
case this x and y represent
our observation and our hidden states
so we define a priorities uh
this joint distribution to actually
represent the fact that this state
corresponds to this observation and we
want to maximize the information in
between them
and this
x y
again is a
so-called critic function
so what does it mean is a function that
should approximate this log density
ratio that we see here on the right i
won't go into the the mathematical
details of this but basically
it is a mapping of the
of two the two inputs so basically is a
mapping of our observation and our state
uh and we want this uh again these
outputs to be i for corresponding pairs
and and low for non-corresponding pairs
so
how do we transition from the free
energy of the path
that we have seen today to our
contrasting formulation
so what the
the first step that we do is adding to
the to the free energy functional
uh a term that we
we assume to be constant that is the
the entropy of the observation so how
can we assume that the entropy of the
observation is constant
so in machine learning we generally have
a data set from which we samples our
observation about the past so we assume
when we train that our
data set so that the distribution over
the observation is fixed
so the the entropy
of this distribution will always be a
constant because we cannot modify that
as opposed for instance to the states
which which we instead learn so the
distribution of our outcomes cannot be
modified and so its entropy is a
constant if we add this term to the free
energy functional
we can rewrite it as a as the child
divergence minus this
information gain or mutual information
term here between the states and the
observation
so given this we can now
apply
the fact that we did
contrastive learning uh
functional is a is a lower bound on the
mutual information to actually derive
the free energy of the past
we're expliciting all the terms out
according to the the previous slide math
we basically have again this kl
divergence term and then we have
this uh the value
of f
between o and s to maximize and then to
minimize all the
uh
again the
the the value of the functional with
respect to all the other negative pairs
so
this brings us to
to again an upper bound on the surprisal
term we see that the this upper bound is
actually
even
higher than the normal uh free energy
upper bound but as we'll see later these
are some
nice property that
explicitly help us to get rid of the
reconstruction and to learn a different
representational space that has some
advantages compared to the
to the likelihood
based uh
representation
so
let's now talk about how can we learn uh
to behave using contrasting vacuum
inference so in the likelihood based
active influence model
what we were trying to maximize was
again the likelihood of the future
observation but under the preferred
distribution so we want to
we want the imaging outcomes to be as
close as possible to the
to the outcomes that we prefer
uh
so this for visual environment implies
that we
we reconstruct what the
what we imagine will happen in the i
dimensional
uh
space so the image basically and then we
compare it to our uh preferred image for
instance
and uh as we see before we can for
instance use a max mean square there or
distance or we can just use like uh
we can use the condition and compute the
likelihood under the preferred
distribution
for contrastive active inference we
again instead use a contrasting
mechanism when we want now the
the future state to be corresponding
with our uh
samples from the preferred distribution
so we want the
the outcomes that we prefer to actually
be
uh close to the to the state that we
imagine so that now we don't need
anymore to reconstruct
what the what the outcome of our action
will look like but we can just say is
the the state that we imagine matching
with uh
the preferred outcome that they want to
achieve
and uh
that's that's what we we maximize
similarity with and again we also have
some
some form of ambiguity minimization or
epistemic value in trying to minimize
the similarity respect to other
outcomes so in this case minimizing
the similarity respect to
outcomes that are not in the preferred
distribution basically means that
you either want to go far from something
that you have already seen before
in order to maybe get closer to the to
the preferred outcomes or you either
just want to
minimize your ambiguity so you want to
be as far as possible from other
outcomes and as close as possible to the
to the actual preferred
outcome that you
that you're hoping for
so
as we've seen before the expected free
energy
can be summarized like this i i'll first
i like some difference in respect to
to the
equation the team presented so first of
all here we we take action to be part of
the
octave active inference process so the
inference process well uh
before we have seen that you can
you can have a distribution of our
policies and then you can you can sample
the action from the policy
and and compute the free energy of the
future uh given
a posterior
on your
on a policy on a given policy instead
here we we make the the actions part of
the degenerative model for the future
and we actually want the agent to to
infer the reaction from the future and
not just compute them as a
as a posterior over over some
distribution of the overhead policies
so we we have now in the posterior is uh
this 80
so we that we infer both the the
the the future state and the future
action
and also the the prior other over the
preferred outcomes that i indicate with
tilde i hope that's not confusing before
because before
the tilde was used to to indicate
sequences but
in the paper i actually used it to to
indicate the preferred outcomes so yeah
notation issues but uh i hope that's not
confusing so the till the year is
basically to say this is the preferred
uh distribution over observation state
and action so this is basically our
target distribution what we what we hope
to achieve in the future
and we can rewrite this as a
as the the sum of three terms so we have
this uh
uh so first of all i'm assuming that the
agent has
no prior preference on action so that
for him
any action that will bring it to the
preferred outcomes it's fine so yes
a uniform prior over action so the
action
doesn't really matter what it is as long
as it brings to the to the goal let's
say
and so this in this way uh we we obtain
an action entropy term and then uh the
rest the intrinsic value is the is the
same epistemic value that we've seen
before and uh
so the one that uh
should lead the agent to
to explore the environment more or
either to reduce its ambiguity about the
environment and then we have the
extrinsic value which is basically
rewards or uh
just uh
just a way to get closer to the to the
actual uh preferred outcomes so the the
value to pursue in order to
to minimize distance uh from the from
the preferred outcomes
in our contrastive expected free energy
uh we we again do a similar move as we
did from the past so here we assume
that we are taking expectation over our
preferred outcomes since we don't
imagine outcomes in the future we just
assume that the outcomes will
will be
according to the to the preferred
outcome distribution so that we can
again sum
the entropy over the our fixed uh
preferred outcome distribution
and then the steps are the same so we we
have again this
mutual information term between the
preferred outcomes and the the state
that we imagine in the future and the
the the action entropy term and
uh this scale divergence between
uh the posterior states and the prior of
states so
is uh
a complex term
i'll say because it basically
should represent
uh the difference between what the what
agent believes it will happen and
and what is supposed to happen in the
environment so normally in active
inference we assume
for the future that the the model of the
world is correct
so that the agent does not control over
over his world model so he cannot change
how the
the environment dynamics will transition
from one state to another so
i i'm assuming here that
this is this scale divergent term is
actually zero though i've seen that some
work this could also be be left there
are being greater than zero but then
then it's basically uh adding the agent
imagines that he can um it can violate
the the environment dynamics hoping for
a better dynamics that it will allow it
to
uh to be optimistic and think uh yeah
the thing that i imagine it will happen
it's actually gonna happen
so here we we don't allow the agent to
to modify all the environment move from
one state to another and we just assume
yeah the dynamics environment so our
posterior over the
the transition dynamics of the
environment is correct and so the scale
diverging in zero and then our objective
uh again
doing the
applying the the contrast if the
learning uh
lower bound translates into this when we
we have this uh contrastive mutual
information between the preferred
outcomes and these
this action entropy term so
if you write it out explicitly we again
have this uh this two term which kind of
reminds the two extrinsic value and
intrinsic value for
for the free energy so we have this uh
the term that actually
should minimize the similarity with the
with the negative sample that is doing
something similar uh to what the the
intrinsic value in inactive inference
should do so basically
trying to to be distant from
from previously seen uh outcomes is is
kind of similar to
explore the environment to minimize your
ambiguity so try to find something that
gives you more information not something
that you have already seen
and so
the the the world model can be
summarized in
these three
main components that we learn we have
our prior network that
as i said before is learned
and should learn the the transition
dynamics of the environment so trying to
predict future states
given
past states and actions
and then we have this gre self that is
shared between the the prior and the
posterior network and this is what
allows us to to brings our history with
us
so just not stop to the previous state
but also to include some information
about previous states
so that we have more
more information available in order to
infer what the current state is uh
actually is
then we have our posterior network which
also has access to the observation and
this posterior cnn as a as i mentioned
is a compositional neural network and
yeah here we have the actual layer
description for our environment which
are
64 by 64. but yeah that's that's less
important important thing is that we
have a convolutional model that
compresses the information from the
observation for us
and this same
convolutional network is also linked to
the to the representation model
that is uh
this
the the critic of the contrastive
learning mechanism so the function that
is indeed
matching states and the observation
in order to learn the
a good contrastive learning
representation
so
the the function that we minimize with
respect to the past is uh
is our contrasting free energy of the
past uh summed over
uh an arbitrary number of uh of discrete
time steps in the over past sequences
it is important to say that uh
for the past the negative samples that
we take
are uh
observation
uh of the
of the same sequence of the of the
corresponding observations so let's say
that we have
an observation in the states the
negative samples will be
uh all the other observations within the
same sequence that are not the same in
time
but also observation that come from from
other sequences so
so that we're basically contrasting
uh the
the current state with uh
different time steps so
uh what happened in different uh moment
of the same sequence of actions and what
happened in different situations or
different sequences
and that's how we
we try to
to foster our contrastive learning
mechanism
then we have the action model so for our
action model we have two uh networks one
is the so-called action network which
basically infers the
the action to to take
a given state and then we have this
expected utility network and this
helps us pursuing what
uh
team anticipated so that the fact that
we
we are
amortizing the action selection process
for a very
long-term sequences by using a
network that should
estimate what the value of a certain
state is in the future
so i'll try to be
more
more clear here so basically you have
the action network to
minimize this uh
this g lambda
t a functional that is basically
an estimate uh
that of uh
of how much value is in a certain states
and how do we get this this estimate
so
this estimate is is provided by this uh
formula here so basically at every step
uh
we provide the the actual uh expected uh
contrasting free energy for that state
and then
for the future uh
we
with some uh
we compromise in between uh an estimate
of what the what the network would
predict
uh it's gonna
it's gonna be the value in the future
and the the value itself that we are
that we are
computing with the with the functional
so that every step we basically
uh
sum the value that we we expect in that
step
uh
we bootstrap
this that's the way we normally say
reinforcement learning so we
we apply some form of dynamic uh
programming approach to
to sum this value with uh what we expect
will happen in the future
and uh
we use this
as our uh target for learning the
estimate so
we basically have the estimate and the
estimate
of the future plus the current value and
we compare the two and we want the the
the actual estimates to be close to what
is actually happening plus the the
future uh estimate
and this is this is actually what is
normally done in reinforcement learning
when you apply the
so-called bellman equation in order to
estimate what's going to happen in the
future by using uh
what you actually know so generally like
the rewards and in our case the
the
explicit uh
free energy value and what you you
already can estimate for the future
so in our experiments uh we compare to
we compare four flavors that
make for uh reinforcement learning uh
using likelihood model this is dreamer
the dreamer baseline so it does a likely
based uh learn the word model and uh
it uses rewards for learning action so
the the river function is uh
is already given to the agent and then
we compare with contrasting dreamer it
is a modification of trimmer using a
contrastive
learning for his world model instead of
reconstructions and then we compare the
two flavors of active inference uh the
standard let's say one with the
likelihood reconstruction model and our
contrastive formulation
so we use
similar architecture and training
routine for all the the four base lines
and the
the training routine can be summarized
as we see here in pseudocode
so for a certain uh for a certain amount
of number of training steps that we fix
intense we are going to train our world
model on the previous experience so now
on a replay buffer
that basically represents our data sets
of past experiences
then we are going to use the trained
world model to imagine some trajectories
in the future
by using
our action model
and the replay buffer as well which is
used because we we need to take this the
negative samples uh for the contrasting
free energy functional
uh and then on the imagine trajectories
we are gonna train our
our action model in order to actually
try to pursue the the preferred outcomes
uh better
and then we are going to go back to the
environment collect a new trajectory uh
using our word model to infer where the
with the hidden state of the of the
environment is at every time step and
using the action model to select the
action according to this data that we
inferred
and add the
just collected trajectory to the data
set and we do this continuously so train
the world model imagine uh some
trajectories
and uh train the action model and again
keep collecting so that we we
continuously improve both the data
collection process because the
the the word model and the action model
gets better and also our model indeed so
that we get closer to the goal
so one important insight that uh that
first introduced before that into an
empirical evaluation of the method is
the fact that
using contrastive learning strongly
reduces the the component requirements
of the model
so here i
i'm comparing the number of
multiply million multiplier combination
operation
for our models and the number of
parameters that we as we see these are
much lower when we use a contrastive
mechanism compared to to using a
likelihood model
and
this is also reflected in terms of
workload time so our model is is quite
faster compared to dreamer
that
trains the the likelihood based uh model
for the world that
uses uh just three words for learning
action and is
much much faster than the likelihood the
active inference model because the
likelihood active influence model other
than
having to to do the reconstruction
during the world model training also as
to imagine
uh the
the high dimensional outcomes in the
future so in that case you have even
more computation because for every
imagine trajectory you have to imagine
all the possible images in our context
that you are
you
you will get pursuing a certain a
certain policy
so it's our model is quite faster than
that
so the first arcs that i will discuss is
the a simple mini grid task so the agent
represents the red arrow who will
navigate a black read in order to reach
a
green square that is placed in one of
the corner of the grids
so
the environment is partially observed
because the agent doesn't know
what's in every pixel of the creed so in
order to find the goal first i should
you should explore the old grid and and
find the the green square or at least
be in a position that allows him to
to see
the green square in front of him
so
for the for the reward model of course
we have uh
we have the highest reward and the in
correspondence of the of the goal state
so when the when the agent is actually
on the
on the goal square it could receive a
reward of plus one
and this is a sparse reward task so for
all the other states the agent will just
receive zero rewards
so it will be just encouraged to to
reach the goal
well for active inference method uh the
way that i chose to define the preferred
outcome is to have an image of the agent
that is that sees himself on the goal so
basically the agent sees himself on the
goal and says this is the position that
they want to reach in the world
and
let's see what happens from a from a
qualitative
level so as i said before
the rewards for for this task it's just
a plus one in the right uh
in the right square in the goal square
what happens for the the active
inference model so what will the the
active inference uh model uh provides uh
as a volume of a certain states of the
agents in order to pursue the preferred
outcome
so we see that the likelihood active
inference when
uh
that is imagining the outcome and
comparing it to the preferred images is
actually giving a very high value for
the for the right
square so this
you know
in a scale from zero one we can say
that's that's a one oh sorry
we can say that's a one but other than
that the
the function it is providing is a bit
confusing because it is giving some
higher rewards in the centers uh
compared to the let's say the
uh
the
the last uh row and column that are the
one that at the least to the final goal
uh
the the the other corner are not even
close to the the gold one so he is just
uh he's just providing a perfect match
and we have no
no control over what the distance of the
goal is because for the perfect match
the goal that's
that is indeed the the correct value
that it is providing but other than that
we
it's difficult to understand what the
what the the likelihood of the influence
model is providing with the contrastive
active inference
we see that there is a different pattern
so the agent is providing
a very low volume for the center so it's
understanding that the center
is of course not what it wants to see
but then it's providing i values to all
the corners
and in particular the highest values
provided to the to the right corner so
the one with the goal because it is of
course the more the one that corresponds
the most with uh
we want what we want to achieve but then
all the other corners also have
a very high value and uh
the fact is that
from i i would say that the contrastive
active inference is is verbally
capturing
uh
more
i would say semantic information about
the environment so
in order to distinguish a corner
uh from from a center of tile is
actually a modeling the fact that there
is a corner in a certain state of the
environment
and uh when it when it looks at the
preferred outcome
image it actually says first of all this
is a corner and that's the way it
distinguishes and then there is the
green uh
the green tile in the in this in where
the where the agent is
so
from from a value perspective we can say
that
a corner is closer in semantics
uh respect to to a central tile to our
goal and then of course when you also
have the the green tile which represents
the goal then you are the closest
so this is of course a bit risky because
it can also lead to to sub-optimal
behavior in some cases but with with
good expression of the environment
it will uh for sure
lead to the optimal behavior because
still the the maximum value is still uh
provided correctly so it's still the
value for the right corner but if you
didn't see the other corner the agent
will will just go to another corner and
say okay this looks similar to the goal
so i'm trying to do something similar to
to what i i would like to do i if i
didn't see anything else disclosure this
is my
the best i can do
so this
these are lights how exploration is
important in order to
to achieve uh
preferred outcomes and i think that's
that also applies
to likelihood active influence as well
because in
if you didn't see the goal you just have
some
some noise
some noisy signal in the center so you
wouldn't be able to reach the goal as
well
and then
here we quantify the performance we see
that with the with the likelihood active
inference
uh the agent struggles to to reach the
goal uh
consistently while our our methods
uh leads to consistent performance that
are in line
with the reward based baselines of
course the reward base
baseline have an advantage because
during training they always have a
filtered objective so even if their
model is not correct they always have
this three-word function filtered
function that tells them yes this this
is where you need to go well our model
uh can take a little bit more time in
order to first have a good model and
then being able to match but uh
with the contrastive mechanism this
process is actually happens
uh fast and uh leads to consistent
performance where we with likely the
active inference we see that uh
it it will probably takes more time to
converge or
it just leads to to suboptimal behavior
so it's just inconsistent according to
our evaluation
and yeah these are two
different
grid environments but this one is
smaller one is bigger but yeah the
results are very similar in terms of
performance obtained
then the other task that we discuss is a
continuous control
task with uh
with a 2d
planar environment when we're a robotic
arm through the penetrate uh sphere gold
so the the red sphere
and
this sphere is bigger in the
the so-called the richer easy
environment which is the one for which
we see the preferred outcome on the left
and it is smaller for the for the
so-called richer art environment that is
the one that we we see in the on the
right so for a reward based
agent
we have
the reward function that provides
when the agent penetrates the
the sphere fully a reverse of one
otherwise when it's
uh off penetrating or just partially
penetrating the sphere it provides a
dense reward that
that tells you yeah you're getting
closer to the goal so
in this case the reward function is
actually helping
the agent a bit more because it is
telling him that he
is getting closer to the goal and he
should just try
in the neighbor area
while for active inference we we just
provide the the preferred
stating environment which is uh
the agent penetrating the goal sphere
and
let's see let's see what happens so
again we have a similar pattern
uh actually
yeah similar but different from the
previous one so in this case where the
the mean square there are
distance from the goal is actually more
confusing as we we've seen in previous
example
so the the likelihood the active
inference agent totally fails to to
reach the goal because it's probably all
the all the states look alike in the
environment because the background stays
the same so the background is not moving
as it was happening for instance for the
mini grid environment
uh the goal is always in the same
position so the difference between two
images is just provide given by the
the few yellow pixel that moves around
and if the model is not imagined
perfectly where this pixel goes it's
very difficult that it will provide some
some informative objective for the stars
instead
our contrastive active inference agent
is able to provide an informative goal
and
apparently the fact that he's providing
some semantic information about the task
is actually helping it to converge even
faster than the
then the reward based uh
a baseline because the reward based uh
agents uh have access to rewards just
when they are close to the to the goal
where the contractive active inference
provider reward function everywhere in
the environment
so when the when we see that the arm is
very far
we have the the mutual information term
that should basically take over and
tells you yeah you don't
want to stay there go elsewhere
and until we we eventually
find the the goal sphere and we converge
to the correct behavior so the the agent
is actually converging a bit faster than
the other baselines and then yeah the
the contrastive dreamer baseline is
converging a bit faster than dreamer one
because its model is
faster to learn because it's contrastive
so this is what actually happens these
are a gif on the right at some point
they show difficult reset so basically
we just see here that the task is uh
is correctly executed so that the agent
is uh is able to match the
the correct behavior so yeah it is
taking a bit longer than expected but
yeah you can see that
for instance in the in the art task the
agent oscillates around the current
behavior but it keeps saying okay here
we see it
so basically the the in the environment
is oscillating in a position that is uh
very close to the goal so it tries to
stay as much as possible to that uh that
point and uh not uh
not be
driven
far from the goal by the inertia of the
of the of the arm
then we we analyze qualitatively what's
what's happening in terms of uh the
value this provides the agent so what's
what is the the objective that is given
to the to the agent in order to learn
here
and
as
as i try to explain the reward is
is somewhere in the middle between 0 and
when the agent is partially penetrating
the goal and is totally one
when the agent is fully penetrating the
goal in all the other situations is zero
for the active inference likelihood base
model we see that the signal is very
close
for all
the
states
so the agent basically
thinks that there is
very little difference between
being very close to goal
and being actually very far off from the
goal and that's
uh
likely the reason why it's not
converging to the
to the optimal behavior for contrastive
active inference instead we see that the
agent is provided a
an objective value is
some
somewhat in between zero and one when
he's a
when he's
not close to the goal and something that
is very close to one when it's in the
goal and in particular when it when it's
closer to the goal the the value is
actually a bit higher than when it
when it's far off
so we see that there is some
again something semantic information
provided which is the the actual
distance of the arm
from the from the right
goal or we can just see it as a
okay the contrastive learning mechanism
saying okay this this pose of the arm is
actually very different from the one
that i that they opt to obtain so let's
try to move to a pose that is actually
closer
and uh
we indeed obtain higher values when the
when the pose is
similar to the to the one that we we
want to achieve
so we exploit the fact that uh some
semantic information is provided to the
agent by using contrastive
learning to
to work on a more difficult setup is the
richer distracting environment
so
in the research distracting task
we have the same
objective as before so we want the agent
to
to reach the goal
by penetrating the red sphere but now we
have varying backgrounds and we have
this structure in the environment which
could be just altered colors on the
tilted camera
and uh we still want to to achieve the
agent tool to penetrate the sphere
despite that so for the for the reward
based agents
the reward is same as before so
being provided for the agent penetrating
the goal sphere while for active
inference the goal here is
is actually a bit troublesome to define
because given the fact that the the
background is constantly boring across
different episodes
we cannot a priori
define
what's the
what the the preferred outcome looks
like so instead of doing that we
attempted providing a more natural uh
preferred outcome with the agencying
itself achieving the goal but with the
standard
task
background so we have this uh
the blue uh
just like uh
background uh with the with the arm
penetrating the goal and we we aim for
this
preferred outcome to transfer
to the
to the distracting setup this is of
course
pretty much impossible for
for the likelihood the active inference
model because of course he's trying to
match this in a
with a mean square there were like uh
function so of course the the the signal
provided will be very confusing
uh very interestingly we see heels that
also the dreamer method fails because
it's based on uh on a likelihood based
models and
as we'll see uh reconstructing all the
the variations in the environment it's
very difficult
so the the word the reconstruction based
word model struggles
uh to provide informative states of the
environment while uh the contrastive
learning based models succeed and in
particular it's it's very interesting
that our mother was able to
to actually achieves the goal here we
see less consistently than before so the
there is an iron variance but still the
agent
is often able to reach the correct
position despite all the difference in
the background and all the structure
present in the environment so we see
that this actually
the representation
uh is actually
learning what the
the pose
of the robot
should be and trying to match it
in the future
and then
here we see some some videos what's
happening so we see here indeed the day
the arm is oscillating a bit more so
it's actually a bit more difficult for
him to assess that he's doing
the right thing but still the
the behavior obtained it's still
quite good i will say so it's pretty
much achieving the goal
and
this shows why
a likely based model will fail in this
environment so here we compare the
ground roof
in the different uh
varying backgrounds and
what the dreamers
or the
the likelihood active inference model
stays through the reconstruction so we
see that
either reconstructing from the from the
presidio state or from the prior state
the agent cannot perfectly model uh
important information of the environment
which in this case is the
the arm pose so it sees where the the
first link of the the robot term is but
he is not able to see
normally where the second part of the
arm he is because he is very uncertain
about that
and then and that leads the agent to to
not being able to actually assess where
it is in the environment and to to
provide the
the right uh a value for uh for what's
going on so uh
using
reconstruction in this environment leads
to
this kind of problem where the agent is
not
certain about the the internal states
and so it's uncertain of what it should
do
next
because the signal
of the state is uncertain is confused
and
so it is also the the value provided by
the
to the agent by the model
and
that's it so i'll just briefly summarize
what we have seen and uh
so basically we use a contrastive model
uh to reduce the computation uh of uh
of active inference is also brought some
advantages in reinforcement learning but
yeah we focus on the
on the contract on the active inference
area where this model brought to
a twofold advantage both in learning the
the word model faster but also in
imagining footer trajectories faster
because you don't have the
reconstruction
then we saw that the contrast
representation learned features that
better capture relevant information for
the environment and this was key
in solving uh both the the richer tasks
and especially in the ritual distracting
task where without this
this feature we wouldn't be able to
solve the task
and then
we will show that
we can
we can use
this method uh to provide
performance that are similar to
engineering rewards
but in a much easier way so you can just
say okay this is what i want to achieve
in the environment provide the the
observation to the agent and the agent
will find itself a way
to reach that
that state without
actually having to provide
a reward function for every possible
states of the environment which
especially in realistic cases is is
usually unfeasible
[Music]
and
finally we have also seen that the
acceleration is very key
for our method to work because we don't
want the agent to
to convert to the sub optimal behavior
that looks like the
the right outcome the preferred outcome
so it's it's very important to wisely
explore the environment before actually
delving into learning the
our preferred policy
and
we aim to look more into this in the
future
so thank you very much
that that was it i don't know if there's
any question
thank you both very
interesting presentation so if anyone
watching live wants to ask a question
otherwise i
have a few
so
you mentioned a critic model
when you were describing the
architecture and that reminded me of
language learning like if someone says
repeat after me and then they give a
sound
you might be accurate or you might not
be but if someone said no it was
you have a negative and a positive
example so
what does that speak to perhaps the
biological basis of contrast of learning
or how these contrast of learning
settings active inference or not relate
to the ways that organisms learn
okay
i i will say that
the the contrasted learning mechanism
though it's not
completely
equal i was added somehow remember
resembles the abby and learning
mechanism where you
when when you have corresponding pairs
of
so the
things that should correspond
you actually want to to strengthen the
link and when you have stuff that
shouldn't uh be corresponding you
actually want to
to wake in the link
so you know i think that biologically we
could we could actually seeing
this way so when you have something that
you
you want to be
uh
you you want to link further in in our
case the thing that we want to to link
further so to reinforce is the fact that
this a certain observation correspond to
a certain state
uh then you you strengthen this
connection well when you
where you want
you want to to be far and that's where
where the contrast i think a bit differs
maybe from this from this biological
perspective we actually push it uh we
push it further which is not always
the case for regular learning because
normally you don't have this uh pushing
farther mechanism so
i would say this could be one one
possible
links and as you said yeah the critic
function is actually doing something
very
very similar to what you mentioned so
you have a
positive
samples and you reinforce so the critic
tells you yeah this is this is correct
and it sure tells you that this is
correct so it's trained to do that
uh we we do it with machine learning but
well if you have a good critic you could
use that
uh yeah it should tell you yeah this is
the the right samples while yeah for for
non-corresponding states and observation
uh
yeah this is not
what we want in our representation we
want this further
yeah so maybe to add on daniel
i think what you're hinting at at um
providing like it should be like this is
more like
a way to
uh to define preferred state so to speak
so and if you translate it to do what
we're doing it's basically saying
um
these observations are what you should
like
basically so so they come into place for
um for trading the action model like how
how do i get to these observations the
contrastive learning part is more like
um
being able to distinguish different
things basically um
and and it's it's more broke than
um than the different um well what you
what you what you like to what you like
to have so the contrastive learning just
learns to distinguish all kinds of
sounds even all the bad ones
and uh and you just now say okay but now
i really want to have this sound so
try to get there i think that's the
the difference here
that kind of sounds like paying
attention to the right details which we
saw with
multiple times like the breakout games
like how could you miss the ball humans
are watching that gif and we're watching
the ball
but we also have
a sense of how to pay attention to the
right details and then in terms of
action to have curiosity about the right
things so it definitely
starts to bridge into some very
interesting behavior
another question was about the action
entropy term
in the free energy calculations so maybe
could you restate what the action
entropy term is since it's one of the
major contributions and also what does
that say about adding terms
to the free energy calculation like the
action entropy is always greater than
zero
kind of like a kl divergence and so that
you mentioned gives some perhaps nice
properties about the boundedness of f
within a lower and an upper bound so
maybe just what is the action entropy
doing here can we just add other terms
that are bounded at zero to free energy
and use that in other ways
okay so i'll start with the
with the question about the
uh the action entropy term and then i
i'll also delve into the
using different bounds for for
uh the free energy term
so uh
here in this uh
in the way we casted the active
inference process for learning the
actions
uh the the key part is that we
the actions are now part of the
the future inference process
so
uh
i i could
i could also go back to the previous
life that's necessary but the the
normally the way that we see this
objective is without this a term here
and there but instead we have like
uh a conditional
on a policy on a certain policy
so normally that means that you
you have some set of policies already
and you're just trying to decide which
of them is better
so
this could be done like using a knock on
browser for no cameras at first and then
just assessing the the one that you
think are best or just assessing all of
them but it's that's impossible for
instance in a continuous action setup
where uh you cannot access all possible
uh policies because uh yeah the actions
are continuous a certain number is
infinite for every dimension so let's
make infinite by infinite and so on so
it's it's a huge
uh
it's a huge dimensionality
in space
so
instead here we we make the action part
of the of the inference process so we
want uh we want to have a
separate model that tells you to tell us
what's what's the action to to take at
every step
and uh
i i what i said that we obtain an action
entropy term uh and that's because we
in in choosing the the best action so in
in trying to to match our actions to the
one that we we should actually prefer we
we think it like we don't have a
preference this over action so we
so for instance i if i want to reach
a certain state in environment so if i
want to to go from this room to to the
kitchen
maybe i don't care what's the what's the
sharpest word the shorter path is i just
care about getting there at some point
or i don't care about
going left or going round right now
when i
when i get off of my chair i just want
to
to go where i need to go so we don't we
don't place a prior over the action we
just say uh whatever action is fine as
long as it brings you the fastest as
possible to the goal because the the the
fastest thing is not
given by the action itself but but by
minimizing the free energy so we don't
want a preference over the actions we
wanted
we want the free energy to this is the
fastest spot
and so the actions are we assume a
uniform distribution over them and what
remains is just an entropy so it will be
a child divergence between
the q
over action given the states and the
this p-80 which would basically becomes
uh an entropy value if you if you assume
this is a constant
because it's just subtracting a constant
to that
and uh yeah
switching to the to the other
part of the question so
what does it mean to us
this constant term here so
is having constant term
useful so
i don't know if there's any other
useful constant term that we call that
so
mathematically speaking having a
constant so
having gone up
an upper bound because of a constant
will then be our mean because you're
minimizing the same objective but then
on top of that
we apply the contrastive
er the contrastive
approximation
and that leads to another
upper bound and as i said there are some
implications of these we get
maybe a better representation but uh
are we getting farther from there from
the actual objective so
from my point of view
as long as
we achieve something that is actually
better it doesn't really matter how how
far are we from the actual surprise i'll
see now
so
in any case we will always
uh get some kind of uh
amortization or
approximation and we will probably never
get
a
100 percent close to the surprising
value
so because we don't have a perfect model
so a perfect model of the world doesn't
exist it's it's impossible to imagine
that we can model every details of the
environment even with uh with a billion
uh machine learning parameter and it's
impossible uh to think that we will
always act perfectly and always get in
the in the perfect route to go uh
using the the always uh optimal action
especially because there's always some
uncertainty in the environment
and there's a
a lot of
things that we we normally want to
ignore in our everyday life so a lot of
things here is not actually important to
to capture in the world model or
action-wise not always important to be a
hundred percent accurate in our uh
movements so in the action we take the
important things that we we get close to
the goal so i i will say yeah if if
there are any other term that we any
other constant term or just any other
modification that we could
do to the to the free energy function
that actually leads to better results
without compromising the original goal
of minimizing free energy i think that's
that would be
a good way to
to address some of the issues that we
that we currently have with uh with
active inference and that that could
also lead to
to improving uh the performance of the
the artificial implementation of active
inference uh
significantly so
that's also why i think that uh taking
advantage of some
lessons that that we learned from
reinforcement learning is actually a
useful inactive influence as well
because uh
there has been a ton of research about
uh way to amortize this thing or
approximate this thing better or
uh
train a better deep learning model for
some something some very specific aspect
and
i think which the the active inference
research should
benefit from this should take
inspiration from this
yeah maybe if i might ask peter can you
go back to the slide with the action
entry
this one
yeah so so maybe to um to make clear
here or
or maybe people that's that are less
familiar with reinforcement learning but
are coming from a more active influence
background so
in in terms of um active inference um as
score christian would would look at it
um
this is basically something that you
should not do uh
so
so basically um
what happens here is that we we see
action inference more like
a habitual thing like i i know i'm in
the states or i think i'm in the state
so therefore i can just
infer my action
without even planning it's kind of
you become habituated so i've planned
this hundreds of times and it's always
this outcome so i just stop planning and
i just amortize this action into an
amortized policy
so that's basically the kind of the
mechanism that that we apply here in
order to avoid planning um all the time
because that's that's the the the tricky
part
uh
we have too much options to plan so we
don't want to do this so we just say
let's amortize it from start
which basically means that this a this
this or queue or approximate posterior
is not only over states but also over
actions and then so the action entropy
just falls out by introducing the
the action in the queue there so it's
not that you that we magically add an
action action entry return to the
formulation it just comes out because of
having
the actions as part of our approximate
posterior but so keep in mind that this
also means that we have an approximate
to steer over our action selection and
this works
um in in these three force flowing
problems because there
yeah your goal is always the same
it does not shift uh it's it's not a
it's also another uh uh
um
if you if you think back on biological
agents it's not like a complex
distribution to maintain from your state
basically just yeah this is the reward
this is where you get it it's always the
same thing so this basically means that
your environments where in which we test
these agents and which also
reinforcement learning solutions test
their agents is exactly an environment
institute for
i can amortize whatever what i have to
do because if i know my state i know
what i have to do basically
things will change i guess if you have
another environment in which this is not
the case where you could be in a certain
state and you could still have multiple
options to do and you and you can only
you can only really know what to do by
planning ahead or by
first
[Music]
forage for information on on what's
happening and in these kind of
environments i i think that amortization
trick won't uh won't help you a lot or
you cannot do it
just by amortizing so it's it's a trick
we did to uh to allow it to work in
these kind of environments because yeah
we have to benchmark against uh some
things and
you have to be a bit on on on par there
but so
keep in mind it's not a silver bullet
that will always work uh we do
deviate from vanilla active inference
here we cost action inference as like we
just want to learn habits we don't want
to plan
but this also means that there might be
situations where it will not work
and then it's not due to active
inference or free energy principle
that's not working it's more like yeah
we did a crude approximation here by
which things might not work anymore
that's interesting um about which
training environments favor what kind of
algorithms and then how that shapes the
perception of different algorithms like
the navigation task what if there was a
fuel tank or there was a
um
larger space that was going to require
like multiple foraging information
foraging trips for example
and um
so then the sort of single-minded seeker
is going to
just die fast but then something that's
able to actually engage in planning
wouldn't so that was a little bit like
to those who are familiar with active
inference and then here's a variant on
what we've seen before
how about for those who are more
familiar with the dreamer
architecture or reinforcement learning
what makes active inference active
inference
and how is it different
well
i think
[Music]
they are
um they're largely uh similar let's say
i think that would be the starting point
because
of often people think about what's the
difference
but
but i think the the main point that we
should rather stress more as an active
entrance community is that there is a
lot more similarities between
reinforcement learning and active
influence i would say that active
entrance is a bit more general than
reinforcement learning in the sense that
on the one hand
um
we don't use a reward function per se
but we we relax that a bit as in we just
have a distribution over preferred
outcomes which is a bit more
general
i would say
and then the second thing is that
instead of
by starting off from the free energy
principle as in
this is the objective that we want to
minimize
you also get the
the extrinsic value term here which is
exactly the same thing as what the next
reinforcement learning agent would
optimize so if you only look at
extrinsic value your free energy agents
will also
do this
but
the the the
the added value i would say comes in the
information gain terms and
these will only give you an additional
benefit
in environments where there is
information to gain
uh and this is not your typical
reinforcement learning environment
but if you look at
for example
the the the the team mace mouse from
call of wisdom these are typical
environments where you can actually show
that if you only go for extrinsic value
yeah
you you won't you will be acting super
optimal so you can actually
prove
almost that in some environments
uh only looking at its extrinsic value
[Music]
given the correct model of the
environment active inference will win i
think the crucial uh
thing that we need to research on is how
do you get the the of the the correct or
the optimal model of your world in which
by optimizing uh your expected free
energy actually
you do the sensible planning
and this is still largely unresolved and
with our models we are
taking steps in that direction but as
you can see there are lots of
issues
to just
find the correct mole
because in in if you just look at the
mouth the likelihood based model should
be perfectly fine but by by the way you
optimize and practice then you see all
kinds of problems like okay this this
this little pixel is actually the most
important pixel of the uh of the thing
and that does not appear so in my loss
function so that's why everything
collapses so in theory every it should
work but there are a lot of practical
problems to to find the correct model
that pays attention to the correct
details or the correct aspects of your
observations and this is still that this
is something that is shared with
model-based reinforcement learning as
well as
active inference uh and and i think
there's a huge opportunity to find
new uh
techniques that can can put forward both
both fields
and we also show this like a contrastive
dreamer in the distracting environment
also
improved performance on the normal dream
so by by having a technique that
lets you build a better model any model
based
algorithm will work
and active inference has this special
notion of
also taking your accounts uh information
gain in environments where you might be
unsure unsure on on what your status
so that's that's where it can prevail
but uh i think in in most of the
benchmark environments that we've seen
nowadays especially in machine learning
uh you probably don't need these terms
you probably get away with uh just
maximizing rewards uh which is in in in
fact also an active inference uh agents
and to some sense if of course if it's
if it's
i'm talking to about a model-based
technique so like dreamer agent in this
case of course the model 3
ones are
these are a bit different as they
they don't need a model at all but at
least for model-based reinforcement
learning agents i think
it's pretty similar to what an active
influence agents would do
in these environments
thank you tim pietro anything you'd add
to that
yeah
i would
like to
to discuss
one aspect of dreamer that we
a little bit overlooked it is the fact
that
uh makes this
amortization similar and it's it's also
similar to what we have done so yeah the
this this is we learn a policy basically
we are an actual network that provides
the correct state
the correct action for every state but
uh
it is the key step that actually
brings us closer to the active inference
formulation is that we
we imagine uh several time steps in the
future so
it is true that we don't uh evaluate uh
long policies and over
over time that that we have this uh this
uh
prior
about action that is given by our action
network
but
it is also true that given the fact that
we
we evaluate the state we we expect to
see and then from there
uh we restart uh doing the
the action optimization process we
actually get closer
uh to to the optimization scheme of
active inference in particular there are
there is a
paper called sophisticated inference
that discuss this when you
when you actually
take an action and then you reimagine
from that step what's gonna up what's
gonna happen there are some implications
of this but uh
we are not completely drifting
away from the from the original active
influence theory because of this it's
just a different way of
doing the action selection process and
in that indeed the dreamer is also very
close to
to active inference itself
cool
thank you
i i wrote down if you don't know where
you prefer to go you are lost
drive fast if you know how to get there
figure it out if you don't and then
reassess continually
and i hope that conveys some of the
similarities and differences
do you have any final comments
this is a very
interesting line of research and we
really appreciate this model stream
hope to see you in the future or should
i say we expect and prefer it but thanks
again pietro and tim this is really
awesome
thanks for having us
thank you for having us have a good day
everyone see